





Francisco Díaz Barrancas

Generated from: Editor CVN de FECYT Date of document: 01/03/2021

v 1.4.3

6d91fe2e84c53b46553ed691384cbba2

This electronic file (PDF) has embedded CVN technology (CVN-XML). The CVN technology of this file allows you to export and import curricular data from and to any compatible data base. List of adapted databases available at: http://cvn.fecyt.es/





Summary of CV

This section describes briefly a summary of your career in science, academic and research; the main scientific and technological achievements and goals in your line of research in the medium -and long- term. It also includes other important aspects or peculiarities.

Francisco Díaz-Barrancas received the B.S degree in computer engineer in 2017 and the M.S degree in computer technologies research in 2018, both from the University of Extremadura (UEx), Mérida, Spain. He is currently working toward the Ph.D. degree in the visual appearance in virtual reality devices.

He is a Research Assistant at the University of Extremadura (UEx) in Spain. He has been involved in several projects related to application of hyperspectral and virtual reality techniques to measure the color performance of LED light sources.







Francisco Díaz Barrancas

Surname(s): Díaz Barrancas
Name: Francisco

ORCID: 0000-0002-4930-4780

Date of birth:

Gender:

Nationality:

Country of birth:

Date of birth:

Spain

Spain

Aut. region/reg. of birth:

City of birth:

Contact aut. region/reg.:

Email:

Extremadura

Extremadura

frdiaz@unex.es

Personal web page: https://francisco-diaz-barrancas.github.io/

Current professional situation

Employing entity: Universidad de Extremadura **Type of entity:** University

Department: Expresión Gráfica, Centro Universitario de Mérida **Professional category:** Personal de Apoyo a la Investigación

City employing entity: Merida, Extremadura, Spain

Email: frdiaz@unex.es Start date: 01/10/2020

Type of contract: Temporary employment Dedica

contract

Field of management activity: University

Dedication regime: Full time

Previous positions and activities

Employing entity	Professional category	Start date
Universidad de Extremadura	Personal Científico e Investigador	19/10/2017

Employing entity: Universidad de Extremadura **Type of entity:** University

Department: Ingeniería en sistemas informáticos y telemáticos, Centro Universitario de Mérida

City employing entity: Merida, Extremadura, Spain **Professional category:** Personal Científico e Investigador

Email: frdiaz@unex.es

Start-End date: 19/10/2017 - 31/08/2020 **Duration:** 2 years - 10 months - 13

days

Type of contract: Temporary employment contract

Dedication regime: Full time

Primary (UNESCO code): 120317 - Informatics Field of management activity: University







Education

University education

1st and 2nd cycle studies and pre-Bologna degrees

1 University degree: Higher degree

Name of qualification: Máster Universitario en Ingenierías y Arquitectura

Degree awarding entity: Universidad de Type of entity: University

Extremadura

Date of qualification: 20/06/2018

Average mark: Excellent

2 University degree: Graduado

Name of qualification: Grado en Ingeniería Informática en tecnologías de la información

City degree awarding entity: Mérida, Extremadura, Spain

Degree awarding entity: Universidad de Type of entity: University

Extremadura

Date of qualification: 22/06/2017

Average mark: Good

Specialised, lifelong, technical, professional and refresher training (other than formal academic and healthcare studies)

1 Training title: LearnEnglish Select Santander- Select Intermediate Level (B1)
Awarding entity: EMBAJADA DEL REINO UNIDO (BRITISH COUNCIL)

End date: 13/02/2021 Duration in hours: 25 hours

2 Training title: From Reality to Virtuality: The science and the art of creating VR experiences

Awarding entity: University of Oulu

Type of entity: University

End date: 15/06/2019

Duration in hours: 40 hours

3 Type of training: Course

Training title: Introducción al desarrollo de videojuegos con Unity

City awarding entity: Merida, Extremadura, Spain

Awarding entity: Universidad de Extremadura

Type of entity: University

End date: 03/05/2019

Duration in hours: 40 hours

4 Training title: eHealth: Tecnologías para la salud 2018

Awarding entity: Instituto internacional de investigación Type of entity: Healthcare Institutions

e innovación del envejecimiento

End date: 12/09/2018 Duration in hours: 15 hours

5 Type of training: Course

Training title: Curso de Big Data y Supercomputación: "Transformando datos en conocimiento"

City awarding entity: Cáceres, Extremadura, Spain







Awarding entity: Computaex

End date: 19/12/2016 Duration in hours: 23 hours

Language skills

Language	Listening skills	Reading skills	Spoken interaction	Speaking skills	Writing skills
English	B1	B1	B1	B1	B1

Teaching experience

General teaching experience

1 Name of the course: Fundamentos de Programación

University degree: Graduado o Graduada en Ingeniería Informática en Tecnologías de la Información

Start date: 15/09/2020 **End date:** 20/12/2020

Entity: Centro Universitario de Mérida Type of entity: University Centres and Structures and

Associated Bodies

Faculty, institute or centre: Centro Universitario de Mérida

2 Name of the course: Sistemas de Comunicación Multimedia

University degree: Graduado o Graduada en Ingeniería de Diseño Industrial y Desarrollo de Productos

Start date: 01/02/2020 **End date:** 14/05/2020

Entity: Centro Universitario de Mérida Type of entity: University Centres and Structures and

Associated Bodies

Faculty, institute or centre: Centro Universitario de Mérida

Scientific and technological experience

Research and development groups/teams

Name of the group: Grupo Orión

Aims of the group: Virtual reality, Extended reality, Color appearance **Type of collaboration:** Co-authorship of projects and their development

Affiliation entity: Universidad de Extremadura Type of entity: University

Start date: 19/10/2017







Scientific or technological activities

R&D projects funded through competitive calls of public or private entities

1 Name of the project: PROYECTOS Y AYUDAS PLAN REGIONAL

Entity where project took place: Universidad de Type of entity: University

Extremadura

Name principal investigator (PI, Co-PI....): María Isabel Suero

N° of researchers: 10 Funding entity or bodies:

Consejería de Economía e Innovación Tecnológica Type of entity: GR18131

Start-End date: 29/05/2018 - 04/11/2021

Total amount: 26.360,25 €

2 Name of the project: Aplicación de técnicas hiperespectrales y de realidad virtual a la medida del

rendimiento de color de fuentes luminosas LED

Entity where project took place: Universidad de Type of entity: University

Extremadura

Name principal investigator (PI, Co-PI....): Pedro José Pardo

N° of researchers: 6 Funding entity or bodies:

Consejería de Economía e Innovación Tecnológica Type of entity: IB16004

Start-End date: 03/06/2017 - 08/11/2020

Total amount: 115.261,3 €

Scientific and technological activities

Scientific production

Publications, scientific and technical documents

1 Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Halina Carmen Cwierz; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel Suero. Colour appearance in immersive three-dimensional virtual environments. Coloration Technology. 137, pp. 38 - 43. Wiley, 14/12/2020.

Type of production: Popular science article Format: Journal

Corresponding author: Yes

Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Halina Carmen Cwierz; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel Suero. Spectral Color Management in Virtual Reality Scenes. Sensors. 20 - 19, pp. 5658. MDPI, 03/10/2020.

Type of production: Popular science article Format: Journal

Corresponding author: Yes







Works submitted to national or international conferences

1 Title of the work: Application of spectral computing technics for color vision testing using virtual reality

devices

Name of the conference: Electronic Imaging

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Burlingame, United States of America

Date of event: 26/01/2020 **End date:** 30/01/2020

Organising entity: Society for Imaging Science and Technology

Halina Carmen Cwierz; Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel

Suero.

2 Title of the work: Visual fidelity improvement in virtual reality through spectral textures applied to lighting

simulations

Name of the conference: Electronic Imaging

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Burlingame, United States of America

Date of event: 26/01/2020 **End date:** 30/01/2020

Organising entity: Society for Imaging Science and Technology

Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Halina Carmen Cwierz; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel

Suero.

Title of the work: A virtual scene with conservation objects with dierent illuminants and colour management Name of the conference: A conservation Carol: approaci interdisciplinari nell'ambito della conservazione

dei beni culturali

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Milano, Lombardia, Italy

Date of event: 20/12/2019

Organising entity: Università degli studi di Milano

Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Halina Carmen Cwierz; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel

Suero.

4 Title of the work: Aplicación de texturas hiperespectrales a objetos 3D en escenas de Realidad Virtual

Name of the conference: XII Congreso Nacional del Color

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Linares, Andalusia, Spain

Date of event: 25/09/2019 **End date:** 27/09/2019

Organising entity: SOCIEDAD ESPAÑOLA DE OPTICA SEDO

Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Halina Carmen Cwierz; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel

Suero.

5 Title of the work: Cómo realizar una correcta gestión del color en sistemas de realidad virtual

Name of the conference: XII Congreso Nacional del Color

City of event: Linares, Andalusia, Spain

Date of event: 25/09/2019 **End date:** 27/09/2019

Organising entity: SOCIEDAD ESPAÑOLA DE OPTICA SEDO







Halina Carmen Cwierz; Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel Suero.

Title of the work: Herramienta para la valoración de la capacidad de discriminación del color de observadores normales y defectivos mediante un test de ordenación de color, reproducido en un entorno de

realidad virtual

Name of the conference: XII Congreso Nacional del Color

Corresponding author: No

City of event: Linares, Andalusia, Spain

Date of event: 25/09/2019 **End date:** 27/09/2019

Organising entity: SOCIEDAD ESPAÑOLA DE OPTICA SEDO

Halina Carmen Cwierz; Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel

Suero.

7 Title of the work: Reconstrucción de objetos 3D mediante técnicas SFM y obtención de texturas

hiperespectrales

Name of the conference: XII Congreso Nacional del Color

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Linares, Andalusia, Spain

Date of event: 25/09/2019 **End date:** 27/09/2019

Organising entity: SOCIEDAD ESPAÑOLA DE OPTICA SEDO

Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Halina Carmen Cwierz; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel

Suero.

8 Title of the work: Hyperspectral textures for a better colour reproduction in virtual reality

Name of the conference: 15th Conferenza del Colore

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Macerata, Marche, Italy

Date of event: 05/09/2019 **End date:** 07/09/2019

Organising entity: Gruppo del Colore – Associazione Italiana Colore

Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Halina Carmen Cwierz; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel

Suero.

9 Title of the work: Improvement of realism sensation in virtual reality scenes applying spectral and colour

management techniques

Name of the conference: The 25th Symposium of the International Colour Vision Society

Corresponding author: Yes City of event: Riga, Latvija, Latvia

Date of event: 05/07/2019 **End date:** 08/07/2019

Organising entity: International Colour Vision Society

Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Halina Cwierz; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel Suero.

10 Title of the work: Validity of virtual-reality-based systems applied to lighting and colour rendering research

Name of the conference: The 25th Symposium of the International Colour Vision Society

Corresponding author: No City of event: Riga, Latvija, Latvija

Date of event: 05/07/2019 **End date:** 08/07/2019







Organising entity: International Colour Vision Society

Pedro José Pardo; Halina Cwierz; Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel Suero.

11 Title of the work: IMPROVING PROGRAMMING LEARNING WITH AUGMENTED REALITY AND

GAMIFICATION

Name of the conference: EDULEARN 2019

Corresponding author: No

City of event: Palma de Mallorca, Balearic Islands, Spain

Date of event: 01/07/2019 End date: 03/07/2019 Organising entity: IATED

Halina Cwierz; Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Pedro José Pardo; Juan Ignacio Guisado; Cristina Ruiz Palma.

Title of the work: Un análisis preliminar de nuevos modelos de mutación dirigida en algoritmos genéticos.

Name of the conference: XVIII Conferencia de la Asociación Española para la Inteligencia Artificial

Corresponding author: No

City of event: Granada, Andalusia, Spain

Date of event: 23/10/2018 **End date:** 26/10/2018

Organising entity: Asociación Española para la Inteligencia Artificial

Borja Rodríguez Puerta; Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Francisco Chávez De la O; Francisco Fernández de

Vega.

13 Title of the work: Colour Management in Virtual Reality applied to Lighting Simulations Name of the conference: International Colour Association (AIC) Conference 2018

Corresponding author: No

City of event: Lisboa, Lisboa, Portugal

Date of event: 25/09/2018 **End date:** 29/09/2018

Organising entity: International Colour Association

Halina Cwierz; Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Pedro José Pardo; Ángel Luis Pérez; María Isabel Suero.

14 Title of the work: Is it possible to apply colour management technics in Virtual Reality devices?

Name of the conference: 14th Conferenza del Colore

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Firenza, Toscana, Italy

Date of event: 11/09/2018 **End date:** 12/09/2018

Organising entity: Grupo del Color- Asociación Type of entity: Associations and Groups

Italiana del Color

Francisco Díaz Barrancas; Pedro José Pardo; María Isabel Suero; Ángel Luis Pérez.

Other dissemination activities

1 Title of the work: European Researcher 'Night

Name of the event: Noche de los investigadores 2020

Type of event: Fairs and exhibitions **City of event:** Mérida, Extremadura, Spain

Date of event: 27/09/2020

Organising entity: Universidad de Extremadura Type of entity: University







2 Title of the work: III Semana de la ciencia y la Tecnología en Extremadura

Name of the event: Reto de Ada Byron Type of event: Fairs and exhibitions City of event: Mérida, Extremadura, Spain

Date of event: 15/11/2019

Organising entity: Servicio de difusión de la cultura científica

Title of the work: European Researchers 'Night Name of the event: Noche de los investigadores 2018

Type of event: Fairs and exhibitions **City of event:** Mérida, Extremadura, Spain

Date of event: 12/09/2018

Organising entity: Universidad de Extremadura Type of entity: University

4 Title of the work: European Researchers Night

Name of the event: Noche de los investigadores 2015

Type of event: Fairs and exhibitions **City of event:** Mérida, Extremadura, Spain

Date of event: 11/11/2015

Organising entity: Universidad de Extremadura Type of entity: University

R&D management and participation in scientific committees

Evaluation and revision of R&D projects and articles

Name of the activity: Review Performed tasks: Review article

Entity where activity was carried out: Journal of Type of entity: Associations and Groups

the Optical Society of America A

Start date: 27/01/2021

Other achievements

Stays in public or private R&D centres

1 Entity: Università Degli Studi di Milano

Faculty, institute or centre: Dipartimento di Informatica

City of entity: Milano, Lombardia, Italy

Start-End date: 01/10/2019 - 20/12/2019 **Duration:** 3 months

Goals of the stay: Doctorate Provable tasks: Research stay

2 Entity: University of Granada Type of entity: University

Faculty, institute or centre: Ciencias de la Educación

City of entity: Granada, Andalusia, Spain

Start-End date: 01/07/2017 - 31/07/2017 **Duration**: 1 month

Goals of the stay: Guest





Provable tasks: Research stay

Prizes, mentions and distinctions

1 Description: Programa Santader Yuzz 'Jóvenes con ideas'

Awarding entity: BANCO SANTANDER, S.A.

City awarding entity: Almendralejo, Extremadura, Spain

Conferral date: 20/06/2020

2 Description: Best Poster Award 2018

Awarding entity: Gruppo del Colore- Associazione Type of entity: Associations and Groups

Italiana Colore

City awarding entity: Firenza, Toscana, Italy

Conferral date: 12/09/2018

3 Description: III Convocatoria Premios Investigar en Ciencias

Awarding entity: Universidad de Extremadura Type of entity: University

City awarding entity: Badajoz, Extremadura, Spain

Conferral date: 19/02/2013



